<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author>Christine Jeanneret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2012-08-22</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>unknown</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
          <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>
          <date>2018-05-17T07:05:14Z</date>
          <name>Christine Jeanneret</name>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Marenzio and the Madrigal in Rome </head>
        <p rend="List Paragraph">When Marenzio published his <hi rend="italic">Primo libro di madrigali a quattro voci</hi> in 1585, he was at the
          service of Luigi d’Este since 1578, an appointment that will last one more year, until the cardinal’s death in December 1586. His connection
          with D’Este has given a fundamental impetus to Marenzio’s career.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> Marco
              Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio. The Career of a Musician Between the Renaissance and the Counter-Reformation</hi>, trans.
              James Chater (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2003), trans. James Chater, 7–11. </p></note> 1585 is also an eventful year for the papacy in Rome:
          Pope Gregory XIII died on April 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1585, and Felice Peretti is elected as Sixtus V thirteen days later with
          the support of Luigi d’Este. During the last year of Gregory’s pontificate, Marenzio published six books of music.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Il Secondo Libro dei Madrigali a Sei Voci</hi> (Venice: Angelo Gardano,
              1584), <hi rend="italic">Madrigali spirituali a Cinque Voci</hi> (Venice: Alessandro Gardano, 1584), <hi rend="italic">Il Quarto libro
                dei Madrigali a Cinque Voci</hi> (Venice: Angelo Gardano, 1584), <hi rend="italic">Il Quinto Libro dei Madrigali a Cinque Voci</hi>
              (Venice: Eredi di Girolamo Scotto, 1585), <hi rend="italic">Mocteta festorum totius anni</hi> (Rome, Alessandro Gardano, 1585), <hi
                rend="italic">Il Terzo Libro dei Madrigali a Sei Voci</hi> (Venice: Eredi di Girolamo Scotto, 1585).</p></note> His output dropped
          drastically after the election of the new pope. The only volume he published is the <hi rend="italic">Primo libro dei Madrigali a Quattro
            Voci</hi> with a dedication to Marcantonio Serlupi, signed in Rome on July 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1585. Not much is know about
          the dedicatee himself, a low-ranking nobleman in the papal court. He was a prelate of the Apostolic Chamber, member of a famous Roman family
          of ancient lineage, who held hereditary roles (called <hi rend="italic">diritto di baldacchino</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"
              ><p rend="footnote text"> Casimiro Romano, <hi rend="italic">Memorie istoriche della chiesa e convento di S. Maria in Aracœli</hi>
              (Rome: Rocco Bernabò, 1786), 231; Johanna Elfriede Louise Heideman, <hi rend="italic">The Cinquecento Chapel Decorations in S. Maria in
                Aracœli in Rome</hi> (Amsterdam: Academische Pers, 1982), 21–4; Arnaldo Morelli, “Marenzio, the Courtier. Some thoughts on Patronage
              in the Court of Rome” in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, ed. by Mauro Calcagno (Turnhout:
              CESR–Brepols, 2014), 227–34: 231; Giuseppe Gerbino, “The Madrigal and its Outcasts: Marenzio, Giovannelli, and the Revival of
              Sannazaro’s <hi rend="italic">Arcadia</hi>”, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Musicology</hi>, 21, no. 1 (2004), 3–45: 38–9.</p></note> As
          Marenzio indicates in his dedication, he was certainly a music lover: “che per esser egli intendissimo di questa scientia” (because you are
          a great connoissor of this science [the science of music]). Serlupi is also the dedicatee of a madrigal book by Felice Anerio. </p>
        <p rend="List Paragraph">The re-editions of Marenzio’s book are either published with the same dedication, always signed in 1585, or without
          dedication at all. An extremely interesting exception is Vincenzi’s re-edition in 1587. This is most certainly a pirated edition, as
          attested by the new dedication to Michiele Boot, and not Booth as stated on the title page.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
              rend="footnote text"> Paolo Cecchi erroneously thinks he is an Englishmen, see Paolo Cecchi, “Delicious air and sweet invention”: The
              Circulation and Consumption of Marenzio’s Secular Music in England (c.1588–1640)” in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca Marenzio’s
                Secular Music</hi>, ed. Mauro Calcagno (Turnhout: Brepols, 2014), 283-369: 285.</p></note> The dedication is signed by Vincenzi and
          not by Marenzio. Boot was born 1566 in Breda and was a Flemish merchant in silk and cereals, as well as a magistrate.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">IBN. Index Notarum Hominum, pars C</hi>. Osnabrück, Biblio-Verlag, 1981
              (ref. to 5106(6) = Koninklijke Vlaamse Academiën van Belgie, Nationaal biografisch Woorden-boek. Brussel: Paleis der Academiën. vol.
              6).</p></note> He seems to have had interests both in Italy for his business, and in music, since he is known to have had contacts with
          a singer in Venice,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> Prims, Floris, “Oud-Antwerpschen portrettengalerie” 33,
              Stadsarchief van Antwerpern (22 August 1932).</p></note> and –if Vincenzi’s text is reliable–also in Naples. Vincenzi had to find a new
          dedicatee in order to hide the fact that he re-edited the same book without privilege, and Boot provided the funds. </p>
        <p rend="List Paragraph">The four-voice texture is uncommon at the end of the sixteenth century. It suggests a look back to the early
          madrigal, as well as the ideal of sobriety and <hi rend="italic">gravitas</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
              rend="footnote text"> Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>, 279.</p></note> Until this publication, Marenzio always wrote for
          five voices or more,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> Except the <hi rend="italic">Sacrae Cantiones</hi>,
              published posthumously in 1616 but composed before 1580, <hi rend="italic">Il Primo Libro di Villanelle a Tre</hi> (1584) and the <hi
                rend="italic">Moctecta festorum</hi> published the same year as the <hi rend="italic">Primo Libro dei Madrigali a Quattro Voci</hi>.
            </p></note> and he will never publish another madrigal book for this texture. The choices of the texts also point to an earlier practice.
          Petrach predominates with eight settings, Sannazaro with five, only one by Tasso, and no Guarini at all. In this book Marenzio uses another
          archaic feature, the <hi rend="italic">tempus diminutum</hi>, much more present here than in any other books. The volume opens with
          Petrarch’s <hi rend="italic">Non vidi mai dopo notturna pioggia</hi> to emphasize the high literary choices and closes with a three-part
          eglogue by Sannazaro, <hi rend="italic">Vienne Montan, mentre le nostre tormora</hi>, an example of the pastoral style. The volume therefore
          is two-fold, both in the choices of poetic texts and the musical setting, oscillating between the tragic and the arcadian tones, the archaic
          and the modern repertory.</p>
        <p>Marenzio’s musical settings is very subtle and works on several levels. Some cases exemplify their sophistication. The madrigal <hi
            rend="italic">Dissi a l’amata mia lucida stella</hi> presents an interesting dialogue. Marenzio creates various levels of complex
          repetitions. The melodic motive of ascending eighth-notes is always associated with the death of the first narrator (<hi rend="italic"
            >morirò</hi>), whereas the motive of decending quarter-notes is always associated with the mention of first narrator’s death in the second
          narrator’s words (<hi rend="italic">morirai</hi>). </p>
        <p>In Petrarch’s <hi rend="italic">O bella man</hi>, an exquisite madrigalism –for the eyes only– is used on the words <hi rend="italic"
            >cinque perle</hi> (five pearls) represented musically by five white semibreves. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Printers and Printing techniques</head>
        <p rend="List Paragraph">The <hi rend="italic">Primo libro a Quattro</hi> has the peculiarity of being printed in Rome, by Alessandro Gardano,
          and not in Venice like the vast majority of Marenzio’s works. Until 1584, he published everything with Angelo Gardano in Venice. Starting
          with the <hi rend="italic">Quarto Libro dei Madrigali a Cinque Voci</hi> (1584), he uses the services of other printers as well, Scotto and
          heirs, as well as the newcomers on the Venetian printing market, Vincenzi and Amadino. Many of his re-editions were published by Angelo
          Gardano from 1584 onwards, but we have to wait until 1591 to find another <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> with him, the <hi
            rend="italic">Quinto Libro di Madrigali a Sei Voci</hi>. From then on, he will again publish all his first editions with Gardano in
          Venice, until his death. </p>
        <p rend="List Paragraph">Since the dissolution of the Dorico house in 1572, there was a lacuna in Roman printing. Alessandro Gardano, the
          eldest son of Antonio moved to Rome between 1581 and 1583, leaving the Venetian press to his brother Angelo.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9"
            n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Patrizio Barbieri, “Music Printers and Booksellers in Rome, 1583-1600). With New Documents on Coattino,
              Diani, Donangeli, Tornieri, and Franzini”, <hi rend="italic">Recercare</hi> 16 (2004), 69–112; Saverio Franchi, “Stampatori ed Editori
              Musicali a Roma dal 1550 al 1608. Vicende e Osservazioni”, <hi rend="italic">Recercare</hi> 11 (1999), 5–48; Jane Bernstein, “Publish or
              Perish? Palestrina and Print Culture in 16th-Century Italy,” <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Early Music </hi>35 (2007): 225–35;
              Robert J. Agee, <hi rend="italic">The Gardano Music Printing Firms, 1569–1611</hi> (Rochester, 1998); on the early years of the Gardano
              press, see Mary S. Lewis, <hi rend="italic">Antonio Gardano, Venetian Music Printer, 1538– 1569. A Descriptive Bibliography and
                Historical Study</hi> (New York, 1988–2005). </p></note> Alessandro started a partnership with Francesco Coattino, lasting at least
          six years, until 1589. He then leaves his share to Coattino, who continues music printing until 1594. All the first editions by Palestrina
          during this time were made by Gardano-Coattino. In Rome, Gardano musical output includes sacred works by Anerio, Guerrero, Palestrina and
          Victoria. Marenzio’s <hi rend="italic">Primo Libro a Quattro</hi> is therefore published at the very beginning of the Gardano’s activity in
          Rome. The <hi rend="italic">princeps editio</hi> is realized with care and do not present many mistakes. The collation with the various
          re-editions is nonetheless interesting, since it provides an insight in the transmission and filiation of the different volumes.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Filiation<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> of the </hi>Primo <hi rend="italic">libro a Quattro Voci</hi></head>
        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Primo Libro a Quattro Voci</hi> is re-edited eight times between 1587 and 1608, mostly by Venetian printers, but also
          abroad by Le Roy et Ballard in Paris in 1598, then by Kauffman in Nurnberg (1603), and eventually by Phalèse in Antwerp in 1607. Many pieces
          will also appear in anthologies publish mostly in Northern Europe, with the interesting translations of seven pieces by Thomas Watson in his
            <hi rend="italic">First Sett of Italian Madrigalls English</hi>, as well as numerous arrangements for lute and keyboard.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> See the description of sources for a complete list and the introduction to the English
              madrigals.</p></note></p>
        <p>Amadino’s re-edition of 1587 follows closely the layout of the <hi rend="italic">princeps editio</hi>, but uses some more space, especially
          for the two-part pieces, where the first part often ends on the first line of the second part. This is a standard choice; Amadino used the
          original edition as a model and knew beforehand how much space he would need for each piece. The first piece, though, starts immediately
          under the dedication for the Canto, Alto and Tenor parts, with the first two staves on this page. </p>
        <p>Vincenzi pirated the edition the same year with the dedication to Boot. His layout almost exactly follows Amadino’s edition. This is not a
          surprise, since both printers were partners from 1583 to 1586 and even after they split up, they continued to share their typographical
          material and privileges. This edition, however, seems to have been made with great rush and little care. It is full of errors in the music,
          the text-setting, and the layout. There are several errors in page numbering, especially in the bass partbook. </p>
        <p>Angleo Gardano published a re-edition in 1592 with a different layout. He uses other ornate letters, sets the page differently, and adopts
          another policy for abbreviation or accentuation in the text-setting than his brother Alessandro. He seems to have used Amadino’s or
          Vincenzi’s editions as sources, since they share common errors and do not appear in the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi>. As is can be easily
          evidenced by the copying of mistakes, this re-edition will be the basis of all the successive re-editions and not the <hi rend="italic"
            >princeps editio</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> See the critical report for the music, for a full
              list of errors and copying of errors between the editions and re-editions. </p></note> It is striking to note that all the mistakes
          introduced for the first time by Gardano in 1592 are faithfully copied in all the successive re-editions. This edition was therefore
          probably the most circulated one among all the various editions and re-editions.</p>
        <p>The first foreign edition appears in Paris in 1598 by Le Roy and Ballard. There are several mistakes in the texts, in particular gallicisms
          such as ‘Toutto’ instead of ‘Tutto’, erroneous use of double consonants, often misplaced: ‘Appolo’ instead of ‘Apollo’, or misreadings
          ‘viatù’ instead of ‘virtù’, all indicating that the printer was a French speaker who had not a good knowledge of Italian. </p>
        <p>The second re-edition by Angelo Gardano is published in 1603, eleven years after his first re–edition. He changes the vertical format to an
          oblong format. The latter was the traditional format for printing madrigals until 1580s, when the vertical format became fashionable. The
          motivations for changing formats were mostly commercial. Gardano using again an archaic format might have been a marketing strategy.
          Reprinting a book almost twenty years after his first edition, for the second time in his press, he might have tried to bring some changes
          to the visual aspects of the book.</p>
        <p>Kauffman re-edition is published the same year and is based on Gardano’s 1592 edition. He creates more space in his layout and contrarily
          to Le Roy and Ballard, has a Italian speaking typographer, who does not make any mistake in the text setting. </p>
        <p>Phalèse uses the oblong format, as he always does, but he too uses Gardano’s 1592 as a model. The <hi rend="italic">oltremontani</hi> seem
          to have had some trouble with the mensuration signs. Le Roy and Ballard often mixes the use of C and cut-C, whereas Phalèse never uses cut-C
          but always substitutes it with C. Phalèse also often inserts an erroneous <hi rend="italic">prolatio</hi> in the regular C in duple meter.
          He is lacking fonts for the triple time mensurations and realizes them by combining two different symbols together. </p>
        <p>The last re-edition by Scotto in 1608 returns to the vertical format. Also based on Gardano’s 1592 edition, it has been made with great
          care, correcting almost all the mistakes in the successive re-editions. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
