<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author>Administrator marchi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2014-08-24</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>unknown</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
          <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>
          <date>2018-05-15T13:57:15Z</date>
          <name>Administrator marchi</name>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>Lucia Marchi </p>
      <div type="section">
        <head>A real <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi>?</head>
        <p>In the same year of 1587 the two Venetian printers Giacomo Vincenzi and Riccardo Amadino produced two separate editions of Luca Marenzio’s
            <hi rend="italic">Il quarto libro de’ madrigali a sei voci</hi>. Despite the close time gap between the two prints, possibly only a few
          months, the title page of the Vincenzi edition claims the authority of the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi>, while the Amadino one
          prides itself on being a carefully corrected reedition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p> The titlepages of the two prints are as
              follows: DI LUCA | MARENZIO | QUARTO LIBRO DE MADRIGALI | a Sei Voci Novamente composti, &amp; dati in luce. | CON PRIVILEGGIO |
              [printer’s mark] | In Venetia Presso Giacomo Vincenzi. | MDLXXXVII; and DI LUCA | MARENZIO | IL QUARTO LIBRO | DE MADRIGALI A SEI VOCI |
              Novamente ristampato, &amp; da molti errori | diligentissimamente emendato. | [printer’s mark] | IN VENETIA | Appresso Ricciardo
              Amadino. | MDLXXXVII.</p><p>I am using the term ‘reedition’ (instead of the most common ‘reprint’) to indicate a new typesetting of the
              music, and not a simple reuse of the printing formes, as suggested by Laurent Pugin. See Laurent Pugin, “Music Printers at Work:
              Marenzio’s <hi rend="italic">Madrigali a Quattro voci, libro primo</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">“Compositor moderno e vago”: Perspectives
                on Luca Marenzio’s Secular and Devotional Music</hi>, ed. Mauro Calcagno (Turnaut: Brepols, 2014), 411–31, n. 6. </p></note> But is
          this really the case? Due to the small press run of 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century musical books, a reedition from the most
          successful collections could be produced two or three years after the original print, but one in the same calendar year is quite unusual.
          Why did this happen? A look into the circumstances of the publication sheds light on the special relationship between these two prints. </p>
        <p>In 1583, Vincenzi and Amadino had formed a printing partnership that had produced about twenty music books a year, among them two first
          editions of Marenzio’s works (<hi rend="italic">Il primo libro delle villanelle a tre voci</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Il secondo libro delle
            canzonette alla napolitana a tre voci</hi> in 1584–5) and the reedition of the I a 5 from 1586.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
              rend="footnote text"> On the two printers see Giacomo Baroncini and Luigi Collarile, “Amadino, Ricciardo” and “Vincenti, Giacomo,” in
                <hi rend="italic">Dizionario degli editori musicali italiani</hi>, ed. Bianca Maria Antolini (Pisa: ETS, in press).</p></note> But
          already by mid-1586 the collaboration was dissolved, due to Vincenzi’s marriage to the daughter of the printer Giorgio Angelieri. The
          commercial separation happened in a friendly way, as shown by the sharing of types and the joint issuing of a number of books on philosophy
          and religion in later years. It is quite likely that the privilege for the Marenzio edition was acquired together by Vincenzi and Amadino,
          who only later decided to issue two independent prints.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"> Christine Jeanneret,
              “ “Dare in luce &amp; con diligenza correggere”: A Study of Marenzio’s Editions and Reeditions,” in <hi rend="italic">“Compositor
                moderno e vago”</hi>, 393.</p></note> Marenzio’s IV a 6 was certainly one of the first items to be printed separately by the two
          publishers. </p>
        <p>This suggests that at some point Vincenzi and Amadino had a common text of the book, a <hi rend="italic">Stichvorlage</hi>, from which both
          editions are derived. An analysis of the variants in both editions strongly confirms such a possibility. Both mistakes and corrections could
          have always been produced independently in the two prints. No significant errors link the two, thus demonstrating that they do not derive
          from each other, but from a common source. A crucial point of comparison is the beginning of <hi rend="italic">Dice la mia bellissima
            Licori</hi> (n. 7), where the Vincenzi print has the ascending step g3–a3 in the Canto, but the second note (a3) was clearly erased and
          reprinted over a previous c4. In the Amadino edition, the opening movement is g3–d4, which reflects instead the original and correct
          version. The Vincenzi mistake is easily explainable: from an original g3–d4, the second note was mistakenly lowered to a c4 during the
          composition of the printing forme, then corrected during proofreading to an a3 for contrapuntal reasons.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4"
            n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> The c4 was against a f#3 in the Sesto voice, thus the correction to a3. On this variant see also Jeanneret,
              “Dare in luce &amp; con diligenza correggere”, 406–7. </p></note>
        </p>
        <p>In this situation, it is problematic to define a clear and unique <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of Marenzio’s IV a 6. The Vincenzi
          print is the first chronologically, but Amadino’s is certainly not a <hi rend="italic">codex descriptus</hi>, a derivative source further
          removed from the original. Due to its direct filiation from a common source, the second print has a prominent role as well in establishing
          the text of the book. Ideally, this critical edition aims to reconstruct the common source, possibly a manuscripts by Marenzio’s hand or by
          a copyist close to him, from which both editions were derived. Thus, this critical edition uses the Vincenzi print as its basis, but keeps
          into consideration the Amadino readings as well. For example, it reinstates the original leap g3–d4 in the Canto of <hi rend="italic">Dice
            la mia bellissima Licori</hi>, and follows better text underlays as preserved in the Amadino print. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head>Inside the Vincenzi workshop </head>
        <p>Of the Vincenzi edition, a number of copies are preserved: I-Bc (complete), GB-Ob (complete), D-Hs (CTBQS), I-Sd (ATBQS), I-Vnm (Q), US-BEm
          (C), F-Pn (B). Two other copies — I-Bsp (complete) and F-A (TQ) — could not be located at the time of this study.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"> Mentioned in Oscar Mischiati, <hi rend="italic">Bibliografia delle opere dei musicisti
                bresciani pubblicate a stampa dal 1497 al 1740: opere di singoli autori; a cura di Mariella Sala ed Ernesto Meli</hi> (Florence:
              Olschki, 1992), 583. </p></note> The seven available copies were consulted and collated. Their comparison offers an interesting glimpse
          into the printing process of the Vincenzi workshop.</p>
        <p>As the studies on 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century music publishing have demonstrated, the typesetting for a new edition was
          normally done one printing forme at the time, each one of them including the pages on a recto or a verso of a paper sheet.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> See for example Jane A. Bernstein, <hi rend="italic">Print Culture and Music in Sixteenth
                Century Venice</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2001) and Pugin, “Music Printers at Work”. </p></note> In the Vincenzi print of
          Marenzio’s IV a 6, each printed sheet contains four pages on the recto and four on the verso, printed out of the same printing forme. Each
          forme was typeset and printed before being taken apart to reuse the types for the next one. In some cases, though, the printed sheet was
          proofread and corrected after some use, giving rise to the many differences found in multiple copies of the same edition. </p>
        <p>These differences — the so-called stop-press corrections — are quite evident in the surviving copies of the Vincenzi edition. As can be
          expected, they tend to concentrate into single moments of the printing, thus pointing towards a sporadic checking rather than a thorough
          proofreading. In the Alto and Tenore parts, for example, the corrections are limited to only one madrigal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7"
            n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> In the Alto there is only one correction in <hi rend="italic">Questa ordì il laccio, questa</hi>, whereas
              in the Tenore there are two in <hi rend="italic">Tra l’erbe a piè d’un mirto, che ’l copriva. </hi></p></note> In the Basso, they appear
          in only two printing formes: that including the pages 3 and 6, and the one containing page 17. In the Canto, Quinto and Sesto, the
          corrections are a little more spread out, implying at least three or four stop-print moments. The Quinto, though, has five out of its six
          interventions concentrated in only two formes: the one containing the pages 1, 3 and 6, and the one with the pages 11 and 14. The
          corrections on page 14 could have likely been caused by a very evident ‘leftover’ from a previous typesetting, an empty staff on the bottom
          of the page (an example of so-called ‘standing types’). Such a clear oversight could have draw attention to the sheet, stopped the print,
          and caused the intervention on page 11 as well. Besides the correction of the forme itself, some mistakes on already-printed pages were
          amended by erasing and reprinting the erroneous passage, or by pasting over a corrected cutout. </p>
        <p>Although not caused by the desire to improve the correctness of the final product, but by a misstep in the binding process, the most
          macroscopic difference among the Vincenzi copies needs to be mentioned. The exemplar preserved at Oxford, Bodleian Library (GB-Obl)
          contains, in place of the entire third gathering of the Canto (labeled C), the corresponding pages of the first book of madrigals for six
          voices by Francesco Farina. No other copy of this print survives, but the similarity of the fonts and decorated initials suggests that the
          book had been printed by Vincenzi as well, also around 1587.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> Ian Fenlon,
              “Farina, Francesco,” in <hi rend="italic">Oxford Music Online</hi>, accessed June 2014.</p></note>
        </p>
        <p>If the Amadino 1587 reedition had already cast some shadow on the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi>, its authority is now further
          undermined by the lack of<hi rend="italic"> one</hi> single text of it. None of the existing copies contains all the stop-print
          interventions, and thus none can be considered the final point of the correction process. A single moment of correction is not even
          preserved on the level of a given part-book. The copy of the Quinto preserved in the Marciana library, for example, presents an earlier,
          more incorrect version of the first sheet compared to the others, where in another it eliminates the standing types present in GB-Obl and
          D-Hs, thus providing a better one. The aim of this critical edition is to reconstruct a non-existent, ideal first edition through a critical
          selection of the correct readings present in the preserved copies. All the stop-press corrections – with the exception of the ones that do
          not imply differences in the musical or poetic text, such an erroneous page number or the standing types mentioned above – are discussed in
          the critical commentary.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head>Later reeditions </head>
        <p>The entire book was reprinted three times: by Gardano in 1593 and 1605 and by Scotto in 1603. Moreover, three other northern European
          prints including its contents, collections of more than one book of madrigals for six voices, were produced in Antwerp by Pierre Phalèse and
          Jean Bellère in 1594, by Phalèse alone in 1610, and in Nuremberg by Paul Kauffmann in 1608. Only the reeditions of the IV a 6 alone (Gardano
          and Scotto) have been considered in the present edition. </p>
        <p> The Gardano edition of 1593 derives from the Amadino 1587 print, although it is possible that the typographer had also a copy of the
          Vincenzi edition at hand and used it for the correction of some mistakes. The Gardano and Amadino prints share significant errors, for
          example the missing minima rest in the Canto of <hi rend="italic">Né fero sdegno mai, Donna, mi mosse</hi> (m. 53). The (occasional)
          collation with the Vincenzi text is evident in a pitch correction in the Quinto of <hi rend="italic">Oh, che soave e non inteso baccio</hi>
          (m. 20), a contrapuntal mistake otherwise hard to catch without the help of a score. Another hint of the influence of the Vincenzi print on
          the Gardano 1593 text is the erroneous mensuraration sign 3/2 that appears in <hi rend="italic">Sonar le labra</hi> (m. 94), not found in
          Amadino, but only in the F-Pn copy of the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi>. In the consulted copy of the Gardano print (Gb-Lcm) the sign 3/2
          was later erased and corrected into C. This amendment, though, was clearly not carried on in all the other copies, as demonstrated by the
          duplication of the mistake in Scotto 1603. A similar situation obtains for the erroneous set of rests in <hi rend="italic">Non può, Filli,
            più il core</hi> (Quinto, mm. 86–9): corrected by erasing the superfluous ones at least in the Gb-Lcm copy of the Gardano print, it
          reappears in the two later reeditions. </p>
        <p>Such mistakes introduce the issue of filiation for the two prints by Scotto 1603 and Gardano 1605. Scotto 1603 is a clear <hi rend="italic"
            >descriptus</hi> of Gardano 1593, a quite inaccurate edition full of old and new mistakes. Despite being done ‘in house’, the relationship
          between Gardano 1593 and Gardano 1605 is not obvious. Although the filiation is evident, Gardano 1605 does not necessarily reproduces all
          the readings of the previous edition, but sometimes shares details – especially in the poetic text – with Scotto 1603. It is a better,
          cleaner edition compared to Scotto, with some clever and intuitive corrections. </p>
        <p> Interestingly, all the reeditions ultimately derive not from the Vincenzi, but the Amadino edition. Thus, in the printed tradition the
          ‘second’ edition had a stronger influence then the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi>. In general, the two Gardano and the Scotto prints are
            <hi rend="italic">descripti</hi>, and do not give any significant contribution to the reconstruction of the critical text. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head>A book in memory of Luigi d’Este</head>
        <p>Marenzio’s <hi rend="italic">Quarto libro de’ madrigali a sei voci</hi> is dedicated to Jean de Vivonne, Marquis of Pisany and ambassador
          of the King of France to the Holy See. The letter, signed by the composer himself, is dated 10 December 1586, only a few days before the
          death of Cardinal Luigi d’Este, Marenzio’s employer since 1578.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Luigi d’Este
              died in Rome in his palace of Montecavallo (now the Quirinale) on 31 December 1586. See Marco Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Marenzio. La
                carriera di un musicista tra Rinascimento e Controriforma</hi> (Coccaglio: Promozione Franciacorta, 1998), 132. </p></note> The years
          in the service of Cardinal d’Este had been the composer’s most prolific, crucial in determining his poetic and stylistic choices, in
          particular the creation of a light-hearted type of madrigal, full of melodic invention and simple contrapuntal devices, which embodied the
          idyllic ideal and Arcadian pleasures of the Renaissance aristocracy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">
              Giuseppe Gerbino, <hi rend="italic">Music and the Myth of Arcadia in Renaissance Italy</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
              2009), 292–340. </p></note>
        </p>
        <p> While Alfred Einstein had suggested that the dedication to Vivonne implied a search for a new employer, Marco Bizzarini’s research has now
          satisfactory demonstrated that the publication of the IV a 6 had been planned (and possibly financed) by Este, who also chose the
            dedicatee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Marenzio</hi>, 132. </p></note>
          From 1573 on, Este had been the Cardinal Protector of the Kingdom of France, and thus in close relationship with the French ambassador.<note
            place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> Paolo Portoni, “d’Este, Luigi” in <hi rend="italic">Dizionario Biografico
                degli Italiani</hi>, vol. 43 (Rome: <lb/>Istituto della Enciclopedia Italiana, 1993). Online at <ref target="http://www.treccani.it"
                >www.treccani.it</ref>. </p></note> In the two years before the publication of the book, the internal struggles between French
          Huguenots and Catholics had put strains on the relationship between Vivonne and the Pope, resulting in a temporary ban of the envoy from the
          Holy City. The delicate political situation was resolved with the help of Este, who in August 1586 welcomed the ambassador back in his
          delightful summer retreat at Villa d’Este in Tivoli. Marenzio’s dedication to Vivonne was likely conceived in the few months following this
          political triumph. Indeed, the letter explicitly mentions Vivonne’s return to Italy as the occasion for the dedication.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Marenzio</hi>, 125–31. </p></note> Through him, Marenzio and
          his patron Luigi d’Este were paying homage to the King of France and his reestablished relationship with the Holy See. </p>
        <p>Este’s political <hi rend="italic">grandeur</hi> was accompanied by an active love life. Lucrezia Bendidio was born in Ferrara in 1547,
          daughter of an aristocratic family with strict links to the court. In 1561 she went into the service of Luigi’s sister, Leonora d’Este, and
          the next year she was married off to Count Baldassarre Macchiavelli.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> Remo
              Ceserani, “Bendidio, Lucrezia,” in <hi rend="italic">Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani</hi>, vol. 8. </p></note> Her singing talent
          was appreciated at the Ferrarese court and celebrated in poems by Tasso, Ridolfo Arlotti and Giovanni Battista Pigna. Together with her
          sister Isabella, she sung for the court at least from 1571 to 1579.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> Elio
              Durante, Anna Martellotti, <hi rend="italic">Cronistoria del concerto delle dame principalissime di Margherita Gonzaga d’Este
              </hi>(Florence: SPES, 1979), 14–16. </p></note> Her amorous relationship with the Cardinal was in full bloom in the years 1571–74, when
          she wrote passionate letters to her lover. On his side, Este was costantly kept informed of her behavior at the Estense court.<note
            place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> Ceserani, “Bendidio, Lucrezia,” and Luigi Cibrario, “Degli amori e della
              prigionia di T. Tasso […],” in <hi rend="italic">Scritti vari del Conte Luigi Cibrario </hi>(Turin – Florence: Botta, 1862),
            59–84.</p></note> Although the erotic relationship might have cooled off in later years, an affectionate friendship, evident in letters,
          gifts and monetary support, remained in place until the death of the Cardinal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
              rend="footnote text"> Cibrario, “Degli amori e della prigionia di T. Tasso […]”, 68. </p></note>
        </p>
        <p>At least four texts in Marenzio’s IV a 6 can be linked to Lucrezia: Tasso’s <hi rend="italic">Arsi gran tempo, e del mio foco indegno</hi>,
          the two short madrigals by Giovanni Battista Pigna <hi rend="italic">La dipartita è amara</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vattene, anima mia,
          </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Non porta ghiaccio Aprile. </hi>Tasso’s <hi rend="italic">Arsi gran tempo, e del mio foco indegno</hi> belongs to
          his poems dedicated to Lucrezia Bendidio, dated between 1561 and 1566, and first published in the <hi rend="italic">Rime de gli academici
            eterei</hi> [Padova, 1567].<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text"> Torquato Tasso, <hi rend="italic">Rime
                ‘eteree’</hi>, ed. Lanfranco Caretti (Parma: Zara, 1990), liv–lvii.</p></note> Giovanni Battista Nicolucci, known as Pigna, worked at
          the Ferrarese court as secretary of Duke Alfonso II, and was the teacher of moral philosophy and astronomy to the young Luigi.<note
            place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> See Giovanni Battista Pigna, <hi rend="italic">Il ben divino: inedito a cura
                di Neuro Bonifazi</hi> (Bologna: Commissione per i testi di lingua, 1965), ix and Portone, “d’Este, Luigi”. </p></note> The two
          madrigals by Pigna set by Marenzio are part of his <hi rend="italic">canzoniere</hi>, collected by Guarini and dedicated to Leonora d’Este,
          which celebrates the same Lucrezia Bendidio. Its titles, <hi rend="italic">Il ben divino</hi> (The divine good, or The divine goodness) is a
          pun on the name of the lady (Bendidio = the good/goodness of God). </p>
        <p>Finally, the madrigal <hi rend="italic">Non porta ghiaccio Aprile </hi>bears conflicting attributions to Annibale Pocaterra and Cesare
            Cremonini.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text"> For the discussion of the attributions see the notes to the
              edition of the text. </p></note> Pocaterra was a courtier at Ferrara, born in 1559, whose poetry had been influenced by Tasso, Guarini
          and Pigna. According to Arnaldo Di Benedetto, some of his poems praise Bendidio under the pastoral name of Licori.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> Arnaldo di Benedetto, “Due canzonieri ferraresi dell’età del Tasso,” in <hi rend="italic"
                >Con e intorno a Torquato Tasso</hi>, (Naples: Liguori, 1996), 289. </p></note> If our text is by Pocaterra, the “harsh Licori” cited
          in the third verse could refer once more to Lucrezia. </p>
        <p>In a wider sense, the entire Book could be read as a restrospective narration of the amorous relationship between Lucrezia and the
          Cardinal. As in every <hi rend="italic">canzoniere</hi>, the story of the lovers is recalled through different temporal and emotional
          phases. This includes a celebration of the couple (Gottifredi’s <hi rend="italic">Tra l’erbe a piè d’un mirto, che ’l copriva</hi>), a
          declaration of eternal fidelity (Tansillo’s<hi rend="italic"> Né fero sdegno mai, Donna, mi mosse</hi>), and the sadness of separation (<hi
            rend="italic">La dipartita è amara</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Caro Aminta, pur vuoi</hi>), a feeling certanly evident since the Cardinal
          was residing largely in Rome from 1576 onwards. The more rationally-oriented side of the <hi rend="italic">canzoniere</hi> contains a moral
          reflection on the ephemeral nature of love and beauty (Tasso’s <hi rend="italic">Arsi gran tempo, e del mio foco indegno</hi>), as well as
          clever arguments on the phenomenology of love (the opening madrigal <hi rend="italic">Se bramate ch’io mora</hi>, Guarini’s <hi
            rend="italic">Dice la mia bellissima Licori</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Crudel, perché mi fuggi</hi>, and Pigna’s <hi rend="italic"
            >Vattene, anima mia</hi>). The exploration of eroticism touches also the possibility of Sapphic love, as sensually sung by Tasso in <hi
            rend="italic">Di nettare amoroso ebro la mente</hi>. Given its position towards the end of the book, after madrigals recounting crisis and
          repentance, Pietro Barignano’s <hi rend="italic">Vanneggio, od è pur vero </hi> could very well not represent the onset of love for
          Lucrezia, but rather its end and the opening to a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> relationship. The closing piece of the book was certainly
          written by Marenzio as an external commission, i.e. as an <hi rend="italic">intermedio</hi> for the comedy <hi rend="italic">Le stravaganze
            d’amore</hi> by Cristoforo Castelletti, performed during the Carnival of 1585 in the Roman palace of Giacomo Buoncompagni.<note
            place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> James Chater, “Castelletti’s “Stravaganze d’amore” (1585): a Comedy with
                Interludes,”<hi rend="italic"> Studi Musicali</hi> viii (1979), 85–148. </p></note> Nevertheless, it fits the narrative of the book as
          a final statement on the nature of women and love. </p>
        <p>The madrigals of the IV a 6 were probably written at different times during the decade preceding their publication, and only later
          organized as a collection. Stylistically, they represent different choices and create a well-balanced mix of moods and techniques. Some are
          example of the light and graceful style so appreciated in the 1580s.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">
              Chater, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>, 113–127 and Gerbino, <hi rend="italic">Music and the Myth of Arcadia</hi>, 323–336. See
              for example <hi rend="italic">Vanneggio, od è pur vero</hi>. </p></note> Others, however, reflect a more sober writing, with denser
          contrapuntal textures and expressive dissonances.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text"> For example in <hi
                rend="italic">Arsi gran tempo, e del mio foco indegno</hi>. </p></note> The six voices allow a frequent use of double-choir writing,
          normally organized as Canto/Quinto/Alto against Tenore/Sesto/Basso (see for example <hi rend="italic">Tra l’erbe a pié d’un mirto</hi>). The
          second madrigal of the book, <hi rend="italic">Di nettare amoroso ebro la mente</hi>, is a Tasso sonnet on the topic on love as war with a
          lesbian twist. The fever of the battle is musically expressed by rapid syllabic repetition on semiminim and dotted rhythms, an early example
          of the <hi rend="italic">stile concitato</hi> of the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Ottavo libro</hi> by Claudio Monteverdi.<note place="foot"
            xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> Repetitions at mm. 34–49, dotted rhythms at 74–9. </p></note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
