<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author>Daniele V. Filippi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2014-11-26</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>unknown</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
          <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>
          <date>2018-05-15T21:04:27Z</date>
          <name>Daniele V. Filippi</name>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>Daniele V. Filippi</p>
      <div type="section">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>On January 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, 1594 Luca Marenzio signed the dedication of his
          <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Sesto libro de madrigali a cinque voci </hi>to Cinzio Aldobrandini Passeri (1551–1610), nephew of
          Pope Clement VIII and recently appointed cardinal. Aldobrandini was a distinguished patron of artists and poets, famously of Torquato Tasso;
          Battista Guarini, Giovanni Bardi and Angelo Grillo, among others, were part of his patronage network.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p>
              See Elena Fasano Guarini, “Aldobrandini (Passeri), Cinzio”, in <hi rend="italic">Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani</hi>, vol. 2
              (Rome: Istituto della Enciclopedia italiana, 1960; on line at <ref target="http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/cinzio-aldobrandini_(Dizionario-Biografico)/">http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/cinzio-aldobrandini_(Dizionario-Biografico)/</ref>, accessed August 25, 2014); Marco Bizzarini,
                <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio: The Career of a Musician Between the Renaissance and the Counter-Reformation</hi>, trans. James
              Chater (Aldershot, Hants, England; Burlington, VT: Ashgate, 2003), 197–199.</p></note> The dedication, entirely constructed from
          genre-specific topoi and clichés, does not shed any further light on the circumstances of the composition and of the arrangement for
          publication. As is well known, after the death of his former patron Cardinal Luigi d’Este in 1586, Marenzio had served Ferdinando de’ Medici
          in Rome and in Florence (1587–1589 or 1590), then, back in Rome, had maintained multiple patronage connections, notably with Virginio Orsini
          (from 1589/90) and with Aldobrandini (probably from 1593).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> For a recent and
              documented précis, see Paolo Fabbri, “Marenzio, Luca” in <hi rend="italic">Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani</hi>, vol. 70 (Rome:
              Istituto della Enciclopedia italiana, 2007; on line at <ref target="http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/luca-marenzio_(Dizionario-Biografico)/">http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/luca-marenzio_(Dizionario-Biografico)/</ref>, accessed August 25, 2014).</p></note> Meanwhile,
          his publication rhythm had considerably slowed down, compared to the years 1580 to 1587: the period 1588–1593 had seen only the publication
          of the Book for 4, 5, and 6 voices (1588) and of Book V <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi> (1591). </p>
        <p>As if marking the end of this transitional phase or, rather, the beginning of a new chapter in Marenzio’s career, Book VI
          <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">a 5 </hi>is characterized by a distinct change in the choice of texts, by a subtle montage, and by a
          noticeable stylistic shift. </p>
        <p>Of the seventeen texts set in the book, four (plus one adaptation, see below) are by Battista Guarini, three by G.B. Strozzi the Elder, one
          each by Ridolfo Arlotti (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1550–1613), Livio Celiano, Antonio Ongaro (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
            1560–1592/1599),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"> Interestingly, Ongaro had enjoyed the patronage, among
              others, of Girolamo Ruiz, dedicatee of Marenzio’s Book IV <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi> (1584). See Donatella Manzoli, “Ongaro, Antonio”,
              in <hi rend="italic">Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani</hi>, vol. 79 (Rome: Istituto della Enciclopedia italiana, 2013; on line at
                <ref target="http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/antonio-ongaro_(Dizionario-Biografico)/">http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/antonio-ongaro_(Dizionario-Biografico)/</ref>, accessed August 25, 2014). </p></note> and
          Torquato Tasso; one text each is furthermore attributed to Bonifazio Bevilacqua and Annibale Caro, while three texts remain anonymous (see
          Table 1).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> For more details about the attributions, see “The poetic texts:
              edition and critical report”. </p></note> Three aspects are remarkable: the absence of Petrarca and Sannazaro (who together accounted
          for fifteen texts out of twenty-one in Book I <hi rend="italic">a 4</hi> of 1585 and for eleven texts out of fifteen in the Book for 4, 5,
          and 6 voices of 1588);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"> They were, however, already absent from Book V <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi> of 1591.</p></note> the presence of Strozzi, which, in spite of previous settings by Marenzio,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> In Book III <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi> (1585) and Book IV <hi rend="italic">a
                6</hi> (1587). </p></note> is probably to refer to the appearance, in 1593, of a posthumous edition of his <hi rend="italic">Madrigali</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> All the three text set by Marenzio were included in that
              collection (see “The poetic texts: edition and critical report”), which, according to James Chater, “momentarily revived” interest in
              Strozzi’s poetry among composers: see James Chater, “Family Matters: Music in the Life and Poetry of Giovambattista Strozzi the Elder”
              in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, ed. by Mauro Calcagno (Turnhout: Centre d’études supérieures de
              la Renaissance-Brepols, 2014), 75–140: 93 and 105. Chater also suggests that Marenzio’s Florentine connections, namely the families of
              Piero Strozzi and Gino Capponi, could help explain his “easy access to Florentine poetry” (104).</p></note> and the first occurrences of
          Livio Celiano (Angelo Grillo) and Antonio Ongaro, whose poems Marenzio will set again in the last books
          <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">a 5 </hi>of the late 1590s. </p>
        <table>
          <head>Table 1: Book VI a 5 (1594): The texts</head>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">No.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Title</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Author / Text source</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Metrical form</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <p>
                <hi rend="bold">Length</hi>
              </p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="bold">(lines)</hi>
              </p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>1.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">S’io parto, i’ moro, e pur partir conviene</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>R. Arlotti</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">6</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>2.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Clori nel mio partire</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>B. Bevilacqua (attr.)</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">12</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>3.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Donna de l’alma mia, de la mia vita</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>T.Tasso, <hi rend="italic">Convito di pastori</hi></cell>
            <cell>Unrhymed 11s</cell>
            <cell align="center">7</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>4.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Anima cruda sì, ma però bella</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>B. Guarini, <hi rend="italic">Il pastor fido</hi></cell>
            <cell>Four unrhymed 11s and <lb/>a rhyming couplet of 7s</cell>
            <cell align="center">6</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>5.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Udite lagrimosi</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>B. Guarini, <hi rend="italic">Il pastor fido</hi></cell>
            <cell>Unrhymed 11s and 7s</cell>
            <cell align="center">13</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>6.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Stillò l’anima in pianto</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>A. Ongaro, <hi rend="italic">Rime</hi></cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">9</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>7.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Ah, dolente partita</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>B. Guarini, <hi rend="italic">Il pastor fido</hi></cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">8</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>8.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Ben ho del caro oggetto i sensi privi / <lb/>Dille la mia speranz’e ’l mio desio</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>A. Caro (attr.)</cell>
            <cell>Sonnet</cell>
            <cell align="center">
              <p>14</p>
              <p>[8+6]</p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>9.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Amor, se giusto sei</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>—</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">11</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>10.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Or chi, Clori beata</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>G.B. Strozzi the Elder</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">7</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>11.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Deh, Tirsi,Tirsi anima mia perdona /<lb/>Che se tu se’ ’l cor mio</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>B. Guarini, <hi rend="italic">Il pastor fido</hi></cell>
            <cell>Mostly unrhymed 11s and 7s, with concluding rhyming couplets</cell>
            <cell align="center">
              <p>17</p>
              <p>[9+8]</p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>12.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Clori mia, Clori dolce, oh sempre nuovo</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>G.B. Strozzi the Elder</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">9</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>13.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Mentre qual viva pietra</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>—</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">10</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>14.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Voi bramate ch’io moia</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>—</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">9</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>15.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">“Rimanti in pace”, a la dolente e bella / Ond’ei, di morte la sua faccia impressa</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>Livio Celiano (A. Grillo)</cell>
            <cell>Sonnet</cell>
            <cell align="center">
              <p>14</p>
              <p>[8+6]</p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>16.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Ecco Maggio seren, chi l’ha vestito</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>G.B. Strozzi the Elder</cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">7</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>17.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Cantiam la bella Clori</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>adapt. from B. Guarini, <hi rend="italic">Dimmi gentil pastore</hi></cell>
            <cell>Madrigal</cell>
            <cell align="center">12</cell>
          </row>
          <note>In the “Metrical form” column, “7s” and “11s” indicate, respectively, seven-syllable lines and hendecasyllables.</note>
        </table>
        <p>The most innovative feature regards, however, Guarini: not so much for the presence and number of his texts (Marenzio had repeatedly set
          Guarini’s poetry since his first madrigal book, Book I <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi> of 1580), as for their provenance from a work of crucial
          importance in late sixteenth-century culture, <hi rend="italic">Il pastor fido</hi>. While de Monte and Monteverdi published
          <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Pastor fido </hi>settings before Marenzio,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> De Monte in his Book XIV <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi> (1590) and Monteverdi in his III <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi>
              (1592), one setting each: see James Chater, “Fonti poetiche per i madrigali di Luca Marenzio,” <hi rend="italic">Rivista italiana di
                musicologia</hi> 13, no. 1 (1978), 60–103: 71–72.</p></note> the latter was, in the words of Marco Bizzarini, “the first of the
          leading madrigalists to set passages from Guarini’s drama in more than a sporadic way”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>, 257<hi rend="color(FF0000)">.</hi></p></note> The present book
          and the following one in the five-voice series (VII <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi>, 1595) “have for <hi rend="italic">Il pastor fido</hi> a
          pioneering importance”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid.</p></note> While the possibility of a direct
          contact between Marenzio and Guarini remains an undocumented speculation, and the circles of Aldobrandini and Cardinal Montalto might have
          played an instrumental role,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> See again Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca
                Marenzio</hi>, 293.</p></note> it has recently been suggested that Cardinal Scipione Gonzaga (1542–1593) could have brought
          <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Il pastor fido </hi>to Marenzio’s attention “as a promising source of madrigal texts”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> See Seth J. Coluzzi, “‘Tirsi mio, caro Tirsi’: <hi rend="italic">Il pastor
                fido</hi> and the Roman Madrigal, in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, 51–74: 51–53</p></note> Be
          it as it may, Marenzio’s settings probably accompanied and fuelled the discussion about Guarini’s controversial play in Cardinal
          Aldobrandini’s <hi rend="italic">ridotto</hi> (and elsewhere, after the publication), and offered a sort of alternative realization of some
          passages, as if on the virtual, polyphonic stage of the madrigal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> See
              Coluzzi, “‘Tirsi mio, caro Tirsi’”, 54–55.</p></note>
        </p>
        <p>As many scholars have noticed,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> See for instance Chater, “Fonti poetiche
              per i madrigali di Luca Marenzio,” 76–77.</p></note> some of the names occurring in the texts set by Marenzio have been systematically
          altered. In no. 2, <hi rend="italic">Clori nel mio partire</hi>, no. 10, <hi rend="italic">Or chi, Clori beata</hi>, no. 12, <hi rend="italic">Clori mia, Clori dolce, oh sempre nuovo</hi>, and no. 15, <hi rend="italic">“Rimanti in pace”, a la dolente e bella</hi>,
          the original “Flora”, “Filli”, or “Fillida” have been substituted by “Clori”/“Cloride”, while the first line in the <hi rend="italic">Pastor
            fido</hi> passage set as no. 11, <hi rend="italic">Deh, Tirsi, Tirsi, anima mia, perdona</hi>, originally sounded “E tu, Mirtillo, anima
          mia, perdona”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> For full details and literature, see the notes to the
              individual texts in “The poetic texts: edition and critical report”.</p></note> The two names also occur in nos. 6, <hi rend="italic">Stillò l’anima in pianto</hi> (Tirsi and Clori), 16, <hi rend="italic">Ecco Maggio seren, chi l’ha vestito</hi> (Clori, this time
          together with Filli), and 17, <hi rend="italic">Cantiam la bella Clori</hi> (Clori only). Thus, Giuseppe Gerbino speaks of a “subtle but
          unmistakable narrative thread” that underlies the book: “the story of Tirsi and Clori”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> Giuseppe Gerbino, “Marenzio and the Shepherds of the Tiber Valley”, in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca
                Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, 265–282: 265.</p></note>
        </p>
        <p>Noticing that Tirsi was the pseudonym used by Virginio Orsini in his capacity as “prince” of the pastoral society known as “pastori della
          valle tiberina” (shepherds of the Tiber valley), James Chater has hypothesized that Tirsi and Clori should be identified as Virginio and his
          wife, Flavia Peretti.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"> Chater, “Fonti poetiche per i madrigali di Luca
              Marenzio,” 77. In his recent and well-documented reassessment of the question, Giuseppe Gerbino has found “no evidence either against or
              in support of Chater’s hypothesis”, and incidentally suggested that Clori could have been “a singer connected with the Orsini family”:
              see Gerbino, “Marenzio and the Shepherds of the Tiber Valley”, 266 and 277.</p></note> In this perspective, the final piece (no. 17, <hi rend="italic">Cantiam la bella Clori</hi>), whose epithalamic character has often been pointed out, should be interpreted as a nuptial
          homage to Flavia, whom Virginio had married in 1589. But besides the fact that Marenzio had already included a tribute to the pair in Book V
            <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi> in 1591,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text"> Dedicated to the same Virginio
              Orsini: see Paolo Cecchi, “List of Secular and Devotional Compositions by Luca Marenzio”, in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca
                Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, 465–522: 501–502.</p></note> a new piece of information further complicates the matter. </p>
        <p>In 1595, just one year after the publication of our book, Marenzio dedicated his Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi> to Margherita Gonzaga
          (1564–1618); the opening piece, <hi rend="italic">Lucida perla a cui fu conca il cielo</hi>, sets the final part (lines 73–85) of a pastoral
          dialogue written by Guarini in 1579 to celebrate the wedding between Margherita and Duke Alfonso II d’Este, <hi rend="italic">Dimmi, gentil
            pastore</hi> (but often printed under the name of Tasso in contemporary sources).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> See Angelo Solerti, <hi rend="italic">Le rime di Torquato Tasso, I: Bibliografia</hi> (Bologna:
              Romagnoli-Dall’Acqua, 1898), 502–503.</p></note> All this is well-known, at least since Chater’s seminal article of 1978:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text"> See Chater, “Fonti poetiche per i madrigali di Luca Marenzio,” 78.</p></note>
          what seems to have gone unnoticed so far is that the final piece of our book, <hi rend="italic">Cantiam la bella Clori</hi>, is nothing but
          an adaptation from the immediately previous section of the same dialogue by Guarini (lines 60–72). Once again, the name Clori is purposely
          inserted <hi rend="italic">a posteriori</hi> in the text (here, instead of “Dea” and “Reina”).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> See the relevant entry in “The poetic texts: edition and critical report” for a full comparison of the two
              texts.</p></note>
        </p>
        <p>As a result of this discovery, we have one more text by (in fact, adapted from) Guarini in Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi>, and more
          doubts about the identity of Clori and the meaning of the whole Tirsi &amp; Clori operation. Is this an old or a new piece? Did Marenzio set
          the excerpt from Guarini’s dialogue back in 1579, for Margherita’s wedding, and publish it, in a revised version, fifteen years later? Were
          the textual changes meant to severe the link with the 1579 event, and with Margherita, in order to make possible a reuse of the piece on a
          different occasion and for a different purpose? Then, why to reaffirm the original connection the following year, dedicating (or
          re-dedicating) the ‘sequel’ piece <hi rend="italic">Lucida perla a cui fu conca il cielo</hi> to the initial dedicatee? Delicate issues of
          compositional chronology are at stake,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> In the introduction to her edition
              of Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi>, Patricia Myers suggested to date <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Lucida perla </hi>back to
              1579: see Luca Marenzio, <hi rend="italic">The Secular Works. 6: Il sesto libro de’ madrigali a sei voci (1595)</hi>, ed. by Patricia
              Myers (New York: The Broude Trust, 1983). Chater, in his review of the edition (<hi rend="italic">JAMS</hi> 38, no. 2 [1985], 376–385),
              essentially accepted Myers’ view on this regard, but provided that one postulated substantial revisions by Marenzio before the 1595
              publication. In our case, given the full-sounding but straightforward chordal nature of <hi rend="italic">Cantiam la bella Clori</hi>
              and the fact that some relatively advanced details of the polychoral writing could easily be the fruit of a 1590s’ revision, it seems
              hard to draw definitive conclusions based on stylistic analysis.</p></note> and further research is needed to answer, or at least to
          reframe, these questions.</p>
        <p>Returning to Tirsi and Clori, and to their role within the structure of Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi>, Mauro Calcagno has recently
          proposed to read the entire book as a coherent narrative, with three alternating ‘voices’ (Tirsi, Clori, and the Narrator) and four
          sections: the “separation between the lovers” (nos. 1–9), is followed by a phase of “rapprochement and intimacy” (nos. 10–13), then by
          “death” (nos. 14–15), and by the “final attainment of love” (nos. 16–17).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">
              Mauro Calcagno, <hi rend="italic">From Madrigal to Opera Monteverdi’s Staging of the Self</hi> (Berkeley: University of California
              Press, 2012), 172–174.</p></note> As further pointed out by Calcagno, this “script” seems to interact with other ordering criteria: the
          madrigals of the first “section”, for instance, are all written in low clefs (c1c3c4c4f4), but other, essentially musical, structuring
          principles are clearly at work (see Table 2).</p>
        <table>
          <head>Table 2: Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi> (1594): Overview</head>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">No.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Title</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Mens. sign</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell cols="3">
              <hi rend="bold">Tonal type</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="bold">Scoring</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <p>
                <hi rend="bold">Length</hi>
                <hi rend="bold">(SB)</hi>
              </p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>1.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">S’io parto, i’ moro, e pur partir conviene</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>G</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>60</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>2.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Clori nel mio partire</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>G</cell>
            <cell>CA[TQ]B</cell>
            <cell>91</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>3.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Donna de l’alma mia, de la mia vita</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>G</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>57</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>4.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Anima cruda sì, ma però bella</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>F</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>62</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>5.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Udite lagrimosi</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">c</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>A</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>98</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>6.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Stillò l’anima in pianto</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>E</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>70</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>7.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Ah, dolente partita</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">c</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>A</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>68</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>8.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Ben ho del caro oggetto i sensi privi / <lb/>Dille la mia speranz’e ’l mio desio</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">c</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>c1c2c3c4f4</cell>
            <cell>C/G</cell>
            <cell>[CQ]ATB</cell>
            <cell>
              <p>154</p>
              <p>[84+70]</p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>9.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Amor, se giusto sei</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">c</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4c4f4</cell>
            <cell>G</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>98</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>10.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Or chi, Clori beata</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c3c3f3</cell>
            <cell>G</cell>
            <cell>CA[TQ]B</cell>
            <cell>38</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>11.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Deh, Tirsi,Tirsi anima mia perdona /<lb/>Che se tu se’ ’l cor mio</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c3c3f3</cell>
            <cell>D/A</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>
              <p>99</p>
              <p>[51+48]</p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>12.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Clori mia, Clori dolce, oh sempre nuovo</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c3c3f3</cell>
            <cell>A</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>58</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>13.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Mentre qual viva pietra</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">h</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c3c3f3</cell>
            <cell>C</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>93</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>14.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Voi bramate ch’io moia</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c2c3f3</cell>
            <cell>G</cell>
            <cell>C[AQ]TB</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>15.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">“Rimanti in pace”, a la dolente e bella / Ond’ei, di morte la sua faccia impressa</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">c</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c3c3f3</cell>
            <cell>D/A</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>
              <p>138</p>
              <p>[72+66]</p>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>16.</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="italic">Ecco Maggio seren, chi l’ha vestito</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>g2c2c3c3f3</cell>
            <cell>C</cell>
            <cell>CA[QT]B</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>17.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Cantiam la bella Clori </hi>[8 v.]</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">C</cell>
            <cell rend="musica">b</cell>
            <cell>c1c3c4f4-c1c3c4f4</cell>
            <cell>F</cell>
            <cell>CATB-CATB</cell>
            <cell>91</cell>
          </row>
          <note>In the “Scoring” column, square brackets enclose voices with similar range. The “Length” is measured in <hi rend="italic">semibreves</hi> (the final <hi rend="italic">longa</hi> is not counted).</note>
        </table>
        <p>All the scholars who have studied this book, at least since Alfred Einstein, have underscored the stylistic shift from Marenzio’s previous
            collections.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text"> See the discussion and the literature quoted in Steven
              Ledbetter, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> “Marenzio, Luca.” <hi rend="italic">Grove Music Online. Oxford Music Online</hi>. Oxford
              University Press, accessed August 25, 2014, <ref target="http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/40081">http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/40081</ref>; Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>,
              293–295; and Piero Gargiulo, “Quella ‘melodia soavissima’. Perle marenziane nel Sesto libro a cinque (1594)”, in <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea marenziana</hi>, ed. by Maria Teresa Rosa Barezzani and Antonio Delfino, «Diverse voci...» 9 (Pisa: Edizioni ETS, 2007),
              277–290.</p></note> In line with the innovative poetic choices discussed above, Marenzio developed a new lyric-declamatory style that
          went beyond the somehow fragmented aesthetic of madrigalism and allowed him to convey in a different, more <hi rend="italic">dramatic</hi>
          way the intense expressivity of the texts. In all the pieces but no. 8 a single soprano is opposed to four lower voices (generally ATTB),
          often to achieve a more direct association with the ‘acting’ persona it musically represents.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> Marenzio never wrote a “monody”: John Walter Hill has pointed out, however, that no. 4, <hi rend="italic">Anima
                cruda sì, ma però bella</hi>, has significant melodic connections with an anonymous monodic piece preserved in manuscript I-Bc Q.140,
              which could have been used as a model by Marenzio; see John Walter Hill, <hi rend="italic">Roman Monody, Cantata, and Opera from the
                Circles Around Cardinal Montalto</hi> (Oxford; New York: Clarendon Press ; Oxford University Press, 1997)I, 247–255; Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>, 191–192 questions this interpretation. </p></note> As penetratingly remarked by Bizzarini, however,
          the book does not have a “unified character”, but is rather inspired by a “subtly pluralistic aesthetic”:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> Bizzarini, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>, 294.</p></note> the touching monologues and laments on
          texts by Guarini and Tasso (which Einstein called “actual scenes”)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">The Italian Madrigal</hi>, trans. A.H. Krappe, R.H. Sessions, and O. Strunk, vol. 2 (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press,
              1949), 669.</p></note> alternate with lighter pieces (no. 10, with multi-voice ornamental flourishes and a dialogic structure; no. 16,
          with dance-like triple time sections; and the celebratory no. 17 for two choirs);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"> For the presence of bichoral works as concluding pieces in several of Marenzio’s madrigal books, see Bizzarini,
                <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio</hi>, 308.</p></note> other compositions experiment with daring chromaticisms and harmonic
          progressions (<hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>, no. 5), echo certain features of contemporary Roman madrigals (no. 13), or even display an <hi rend="italic">arioso</hi> character (no. 9).</p>
        <p>Compared to some of the most famous books by Marenzio, such as the first and the last in the series <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi>, Book VI has
          apparently had a modest success:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> See Gargiulo, “Quella ‘melodia
              soavissima’”, 281–282. </p></note> republished in its entirety (with the exception of no. 17) in the comprehensive collections of
          Marenzio’s five-voice madrigals issued by Kauffmann in Nuremberg (1601) and by the Phalèse firm in Antwerp (1609 and 1632),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text"> See “Description of the sources and consulted copies”.</p></note> it has had
          otherwise no reprints in anthologies. Madrigal no. 13, <hi rend="italic">Mentre qual viva pietra</hi>, formed the basis for one of Girolamo
          Cavaglieri’s <hi rend="italic">contrafacta</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> In RISM 1616<hi rend="superscript">8</hi>: see the “Critical report”.</p></note> and, according to Chater,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> See James Chater, <hi rend="italic">Luca Marenzio and the Italian Madrigal, 1577–1593</hi> (Ann Arbor, Mich.: UMI,
              1981), Appendix II, 208.</p></note> worked as a model for a Magnificat <hi rend="italic">a 6</hi> by Michael Praetorius.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text"> A <hi rend="italic">Missa Mentre qual viva pietra</hi> by G. Belli (<hi rend="italic">Missae sacrae</hi>, 1608) is probably based on the same madrigal, given that no other setting of this text is known, but
              this information needs to be verified.</p></note> No. 3, <hi rend="italic">Donna de l’alma mia, de la mia vita</hi>, was intabulated for
          the lute by Joachim van den Hove in his <hi rend="italic">Delitiae mvsicae</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> RISM 1612<hi rend="superscript">18</hi>: see the “Critical report”.</p></note> A handful of pieces were copied in
          English manuscripts<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"> See Paolo Cecchi, “‘Delicious air and sweet invention’:
              The Circulation and Consumption of Marenzio’s Secular Music in England (c. 1588–1640)”, in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca
                Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, 283–370: 347–350.</p></note> (but a comprehensive mapping of Marenzio’s presence in manuscript sources
          is still to be done). </p>
        <p>On the other hand, Severo Bonini, in his <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Discorsi e regole </hi>(<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1653),
          singles out this book as an example of Marenzio’s proficiency in what he calls “terzo ordine” and <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
          corresponds to Monteverdi’s <hi rend="italic">seconda pratica</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text"> See
              Gargiulo, “Quella ‘melodia soavissima’”, 282–283. Gargiulo reads Bonini’s passage as a reference to no. 1, <hi rend="italic">S’io parto,
                i’ moro, e pur partir conviene</hi>, only, but in my opinion Bonini’s phrasing refers to the whole book, identified through the
              opening piece, as it happens elsewhere in his text. </p></note> Furthermore, a systematic investigation about the texts set by Marenzio
          in Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi> and their concordances in other music collections indirectly attests to a favorable reception of the
          book: Marenzio was often the first to choose texts which later became popular among madrigalists (a clear example is no. 5, <hi rend="italic">Udite lagrimosi</hi>). </p>
        <p>* * *</p>
        <p>The <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi> of the book, issued by Angelo Gardano in Venice in 1594,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text"> See “Description of the sources and consulted copies”.</p></note> is a remarkably accurate and correct edition,
          and the extant re-editions of 1603 and 1614 are also substantially reliable. The 1614 re-edition may derive directly from the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi>, based on the variants and on details of the mise-en-page and of ‘calibration’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text"> The 1614 print is in vertical format, while the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi> is in
              oblong format: often, however, the content of the first two staves of the 1614 page exactly corresponds to that of the first staff in
              the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi> (in other cases, three staves of 1614 accommodate the content of two staves of the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi>). For the term ‘calibration’ to indicate the operations of organizing the page layout and calculating the distribution
              of the music in the book, see Laurent Pugin, “Music Printers at Work: Marenzio’s <hi rend="italic">Madrigali a quattro voci, libro
                primo</hi>”, in <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Luca Marenzio’s Secular Music</hi>, 409–430: 411.</p></note> Pending a systematic
          recognition of the extant copies of the <hi rend="italic">princeps</hi> with Aruspix,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"> See Pugin, “Music Printers at Work”, 415–417.</p></note> I have been able to detect only two cases of stop-press
          correction. One occurs on the dedication page of the Basso partbook: while the copy held at Modena, Biblioteca Estense Universitaria
          (I-MOe), has a misprint in the signature: “Luca Marenzo” (!), all the other consulted copies have the correct reading. The other case
          regards page 8 in the Tenore partbook (madrigal no. 8, <hi rend="italic">Ben ho del caro oggetto i sensi privi</hi>): in the copies held in
          Berkeley, Brussels, and London, the d3 at m. 16 is a <hi rend="italic">semiminima</hi> instead of a <hi rend="italic">minima</hi>; the other
          consulted copies have the correct reading. </p>
        <p align="right">
          <hi rend="italic">Boston (Mass.)-Veruno (Italy), Summer 2014</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
