<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author>DVF</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2015-04-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>unknown</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
          <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>
          <date>2018-05-17T06:33:28Z</date>
          <name>DVF</name>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>
          <hi rend="normalweight">Sources used for collation</hi>
        </head>
        <div>
          <head>
            <hi rend="normalweight">Venice: Angelo Gardano, 1594. AnGa-1594</hi>
          </head>
          <p>DI LVCA MARENZIO | IL SESTO LIBRO DE MADRIGALI | A CINQVE VOCI, | Nouamente posto in luce. | CON PRIVILEGIO. | [printer’s mark] | In
            Venetia Appresso Angelo Gardano. | M. D. LXXXXIIII.</p>
          <p>Set of 5 partbooks in 4°, oblong format: CANTO ([A]/A<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–C/C<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>),TENORE (D/D<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–F/F<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>), both of (2) + 21 + (1) pp.; ALTO (G/G<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–I/I<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>) of (2) + 20 [<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">recte </hi>21] + (1) pp.; BASSO (K/K<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–M/M<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>) of (2) + 21 + (1) pp.; QVINTO (N/N<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–P/P<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>) of
            (2) + 20 [<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">recte </hi>21] + (1) pp.</p>
          <p>The first signature of every gathering (except for the title page) bears the inscription “Madrigali di Luca Marentio Lib. 6. A 5.” The
            title page bears an ornament in the upper part, which frames the voice indication.</p>
          <p>On p. (2): dedication to Cinzio Aldobrandini.</p>
          <p>ALL’ILLUSTRISS[IMO] E REVERENDISS[IMO]</p>
          <p>SIGNOR MIO PATRON COLENDISSIMO</p>
          <p>IL SIGNORE CINZIO ALDOBRANDINO</p>
          <p>Cardinale di San Giorgio</p>
          <p>Io confesso ingenuamente che questi Madrigali, i quali ornati del nome di V[ostra] S[ignoria] Illustriss[ima] escon pur ora in luce, son
            così frutti del mio sterile ingegno come della feconda benignità sua. Perciò che l’animo mio, risvegliato da’ continui favori che mi fa, e
            illustrato dal chiaro dell’infinita virtù di V[ostra] Sig[noria] Illustriss[ima], per la quale quasi nuovo e splendido Sole è più tosto
            invidiata che imitata, va di mano in mano producendo effetti non conforme alla virtù che lo muove, ma secondo la disposizion del mio
            imperfetto. Egli è ben vero che, da che io conobbi che non l’era discara la servitù mia, ho procurato con ogni industria (e forse indarno)
            di far derivar dall’eroiche parti che risplendono in lei qualche perfezion nelle cose mie. E s’io non mi ci sono avanzato come volevo,
            doverà supplire l’abbondanza della devozion dell’animo al mancamento dell’eccellenza dell’arte. E però supplico V[ostra] Sig[noria]
            Illustriss[ima] che gradisca che queste mie fatiche (com’effetti delle tante grazie ch’io ricevo da lei) si abbelliscano del chiarissimo
            nome suo, per render me più caro a me stesso, mentre con ogni studio procaccerò di mostrarmi non indegno di quella grazia della quale per
            sua propria bontà m’ha fatto partecipe. Bacio umilmente le mani di V[ostra] Sig[noria] Illustriss[ima] e le prego dal Signor Dio ogni
            prosperità maggiore. Di Roma il dì Primo Genaro 1594.</p>
          <p>Di V[ostra] Sig[noria] Illustrissima e Reverendiss[ima]</p>
          <p> Devotiss[imo] e obligatiss[imo] Servitore</p>
          <p> Luca Marenzio </p>
          <lb/>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Preserved copies</hi> (complete unless stated otherwise): A-Wn, B-Br, D-As, F-Pn, GB-Lbl (CATQ), I-Bc, I-Bsp (CATQ),
            I-MOe, I-Sd (T), I-ST (C), IRL-Dm (B), NL-DHgm (A), US-BEm (CT), US-BU (Q), US-CAh (Q)</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">References</hi>: RISM A/1 M557, NV 1629, <hi rend="italic">MMB</hi> 274</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Consulted copies</hi>: I-MOe (for systematic collation); A-Wn, B-Br, F-Pn, GB-Lbl (CATQ), I-Bc, I-Sd (T), I-ST (C),
            IRL-Dm (B), US-BEm (CT), US-CAh (Q) (for cross-checking).</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Comments</hi>: In the copy of the princeps at I-MOe, Basso partbook, the composer’s signature under the dedication is
            misspelled as “Marenzo”. All the other consulted copied have the correct reading.</p>
          <p>The copy preserved in I-MOe has the handwritten inscription “Eugenio Cagnani” on the title page of each partbook. It is, thus, tempting
            to identify the previous owner of the set with the namesake man of letters (1577–1614), treasurer at the Gonzaga court, member of the
            Accademia degli Invaghiti, and editor of a <hi rend="italic">Raccolta d’alcune rime di scrittori mantovani</hi> (Mantua, 1612).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> See Claudio Mutini, “Cagnani, Eugenio,” in <hi rend="italic">Dizionario
                  Biografico degli Italiani</hi>, vol. 16 (Rome: Istituto della Enciclopedia italiana, 1973; on line at <ref target="http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/eugenio-cagnani_(Dizionario_Biografico)/">http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/eugenio-cagnani_(Dizionario_Biografico)/</ref>, accessed August 25, 2014).</p></note></p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>
            <hi rend="normalweight">Venice: Angelo Gardano, 1603. AnGa-1603</hi>
          </head>
          <p>DI LVCA MARENZIO | IL SESTO LIBRO DE MADRIGALI | A CINQVE VOCI. | Nouamente Ristampato. | CON PRIVILEGIO. | [printer’s mark] | IN
            VENETIA. | Appresso Angelo Gardano. | M. D. CIII. </p>
          <p>Set of 5 partbooks in 4°, oblong format: CANTO ([A]/A<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–C/C<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>),TENORE (D/D<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–F/F<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>), ALTO (G/G<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–I/I<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>), BASSO
              (K/K<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–M/M<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>), QVINTO (N/N<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>–P/P<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>),
            all of (2) + 21 + (1) pp.</p>
          <p>The first signature of every gathering (except for the title page) bears the inscription “Madrigali Di Luca Marenzio. Lib. 6. A 5.” The
            title page bears an ornament in the upper part (upside down in the consulted copy of the Canto), which frames the voice indication.</p>
          <p>No dedication; p. (2) is blank in all the partbooks.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Preserved copies </hi>(complete unless stated otherwise): A-Wn (CTQ), D-Rp (C), F-Phanson, F-Pn,
            GB-Lbl (CTB), I-Bc, I-Nc (CAB), I-Sac (C), I-Vnm</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">References</hi>: RISM A/1 M558, NV 1630, <hi rend="italic">MMB</hi> 275</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Consulted copy</hi>: I-Bc</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>
            <hi rend="normalweight">Venice: Angelo Gardano, 1604.</hi>
          </head>
          <p>Lost (according to Nuovo Vogel and Mischiati, an incomplete copy of the Canto was preserved in the Borghese Library in Rome).</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">References</hi>: NV 1631, <hi rend="italic">MMB</hi> 276</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>
            <hi rend="normalweight">Venice: Magni-Gardano, 1614. Ma-Ga-1614</hi>
          </head>
          <p>DI LVCA MARENZIO | IL SESTO LIBRO | DE MADRIGALI | A CINQVE VOCI | <hi rend="italic">Nouamente ristampato</hi>. | CON PRIVILEGIO. |
            [printer’s mark] | STAMPA DEL GARDANO | IN VENETIA. M DC XIIII. | Ære Bartholomæi Magni. </p>
          <p>Set of 5 partbooks in 12°, upright format: CANTO ([A]/A–A<hi rend="subscript">6</hi>), TENORE (B–B<hi rend="subscript">6</hi>), ALTO
              (C–C<hi rend="subscript">6</hi>), BASSO (D–D<hi rend="subscript">6</hi>), QVINTO (E–E<hi rend="subscript">6</hi>), all of (2) + 21 + (1)
            pp.</p>
          <p>The signature in gatherings with an odd number (except for the title page) bears the inscription “Madrigali di Luca Marentio Lib. 6. A
            5.” The title page bears an ornamented frame. The voice indication is framed within the upper section of the title page.</p>
          <p>No dedication; p. (2) is blank in all the partbooks.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Preserved copies</hi> (complete unless stated otherwise): GB-Lbl (1 compl. set + B), I-Vnm (Q), I-VEcap</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">References</hi>: RISM A/1 M559, NV 1632, <hi rend="italic">MMB</hi> 277</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Consulted copies</hi>: I-VEcap (for systematic collation), GB-Lbl (for cross-checking)</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>
          <hi rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve">Other sources </hi>
        </head>
        <p>The book is reprinted in its entirety (with the exception of the eight-voice madrigal no. 17) in the following comprehensive collections of
          Marenzio’s five-voice madrigals:</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Ka-1601 = </hi><hi rend="italic">Lucae Marentii, musicii celeberrimi, madrigalia quinque vocum, anteà Venetiis, diversis
            temporibus, novem separatis edita libris, jam verò, commodioris usus caussâ, uno volumine conjunctim excusa</hi> [sic] [contains books
          I–IX for 5vv.]. Paul Kauffmann, Nuremberg 1601.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Ph-1609 = </hi><hi rend="italic">Di Luca Marenzio … Il sesto, settimo, ottavo et nono libro, suo
            testamento, de madrigali a cinque voci</hi>. Pierre Phalèse, Antwerp 1609.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Ph-heirs-1632 = </hi><hi rend="italic">Di Luca Marenzio … Il sesto, settimo, ottavo et nono libro,
            suo testamento, de madrigali a cinque voci</hi> [with an added basso continuo part]. Heirs of Pierre Phalèse, Antwerp 1632.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
