<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>MODE general editorial criteria</title>
        <author>Mauro Calcagno</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date/>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>no publication statement available</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change>
          <name/>
          <date/>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Music</head>
        <p>The objectives of MODE concerning the presentation of the musical text of Marenzio&#x2019;s secular works are: a) to provide its users with
          a text derived from a systematic collation of the sources, including the surviving copies of the first edition, and b) to display the
          musical text in a form that facilitates the study and the performance of the music.</p>
        <p>This section lays out the editorial policy. The critical apparatus of
          individual books includes a discussion of specific editorial issues affecting specific points in the score (such as errors or conflicting
          variants).</p>
        <div>
          <head>Clefs</head>
          <p>The original clefs have been substituted with modern ones (treble, transposed treble and bass clefs) to facilitate reading. Original clefs are however visible through the digital interface (left-side bar, under &#x201C;Options&#x201D;).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Mensurations and proportions</head>
          <p>Original mensuration signs and proportions have been maintained. Time signatures should be read as such and not as modern equivalents.
          	All original note values have been retained. Most pieces are written with the mensuration sign <hi rend="musica">C</hi>, implying a <hi rend="italic">tactus</hi>
            of a semibreve. These pieces usually have shorter note values (ranging from the semibreve to the semifusa). Some madrigals are written in
            <hi rend="musica">c</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">alla breve</hi>), normally implying a <hi rend="italic">tactus</hi> of a breve with longer note-values (from
            the breve to the fusa), for example <hi rend="italic">Udite, lagrimosi amanti</hi> in Book VI <hi rend="italic">a 5</hi>.</p>
          <p>Ternary sections requiring a <hi rend="italic">tactus inaequalis</hi> are indicated by mensuration signs or proportions appearing in
            various forms. Proportion signs appearing in the course of a piece are maintained in the score. Equivalence values are provided above the staff.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Barring</head>
          <p>Barring not present in the original partbooks has been added in the modern edition with respect to the original <hi rend="italic">tactus</hi>. Decisions on barring have been made by the editors according not only to mensural signs but also to note values, rhythmic
            groupings, and the use of rests.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Coloration</head>
          <p>Blackened notes have been marked by half-brackets and resolved as triplets. Minor color (black semibrevis plus black minima) has been
            transcribed as a dotted half note followed by a quarter note; minor color at the level of brevis (black brevis plus black semibrevis) has
            been transcribed as a dotted whole note followed by a half note.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Beaming</head>
          <p>Beaming follows modern conventions.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ligatures</head>
          <p>Ligatures have been resolved with their respective note values. In the score, the notes originally ligated appear with the sign
            (&#x250D;&#x2511;). The most common ligature in Marenzio&#x2019;s time was the <hi rend="italic">cum opposita proprietate</hi> type. This has been transcribed as two semibreves. In some
            rare cases the notes tied together in a ligature are blackened. Other types of ligatures are discussed in the critical apparatus.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Accidentals</head>
          <p>In line with sixteenth-century practice, accidentals apply only to adjacent notes. The edition inserts &#x201C;cautionary
            accidentals&#x201D; above the staff. They have been added either to resolve ambiguous passages, or to supply alterations that
            are only implied in the original notation, as typically occurs at cadences. Sharps or flats used as cancellation signs in the original
            notation have been rendered as natural signs without further mention in the critical notes.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ties and dotted notes</head>
          <p>If dotted notes or long note values extend over a bar, they have been transcribed as tied notes without further mention in the critical
            notes.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Text</head>
        <p>The poetic text appearing in the critical apparatus is as close as possible to the one underlaid in the score.</p>
        <p>These interventions have been done tacitly:</p>
        <p>1. The letters <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u</hi> are graphically differentiated by following modern spelling.</p>
        <p>2. Only a single form of lowercase <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is used.</p>
        <p>3. Abbreviations are written out in full.</p>
        <p>4. The ampersand and the Latinism <hi rend="italic">et</hi> are written out as <hi rend="italic">e</hi> before words beginning with a
          consonant or a vowel other than <hi rend="italic">e</hi>. They are changed to <hi rend="italic">ed</hi> before words beginning with <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</p>
        <p>5. Accents have been normalized according to modern usage. Phonic accents have been introduced in case of ambiguity of meaning (e.g.,
        	<hi rend="italic">v&#xF2;to</hi>).</p>
        <p>6. Apostrophes have been normalized according to modern usage. The apostrophe is introduced&#x2013;or kept, if present&#x2013;in the presence of elision
        	(e.g., <hi rend="italic">ond&#x2019;egli</hi>), apocope (e.g., <hi rend="italic">co&#x2019;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">di&#x2019;</hi>), or aphaeresis of the masculine definite article (e.g., <hi rend="italic">&#x2019;l</hi>). In the
          original partbooks, it is common to find the apostrophe to indicate synaloepha even in the absence of an elision; this has always been
          eliminated.</p>
        <p>7. Elisions: because the same word often appears differently among the original partbooks (with the final vowel elided or present), the
          version presented by the majority of the voices is adopted and extended to all the other voices. In cases in which the elided and non-elided
          forms are split among an equal number of partbooks, the non-elided version is adopted for all the voices. The elided vowel is reintroduced
          only when there is ambiguity in meaning, pronunciation, or punctuation. In these last cases, the reintroduced vowel appears in italics.</p>
        <p>8. Because the same word often appears differently among the partbooks as including either a single or a double consonant (geminates), the
          version presented by the majority of the voices is adopted and extended to all the other voices. In cases in which the two versions are
          split among an equal number of partbooks, the version adopted for all the voices is the one closest to modern usage.</p>
        <p>9. Capitalization conforms to modern usage. Capitals are maintained at the beginning of a line. Capitals are kept in the case of
          personifications (e. g., <hi rend="italic">Amor</hi>).</p>
        <p>10. In the text under the notes, repeated words, lines, or syntagmas are separated by a comma, with the repeated segment starting with a
          lowercase letter even if it includes the beginning of a line (which is otherwise capitalized). Repeated segments that are not present as
          such in the underlaid text of the original partbooks appear in italics.</p>
        <p>11. Punctuation marks (periods, commas, colons, and semicolons, as well as question, exclamation and quotation marks) are introduced or
          modified according to modern usage.</p>
        <p>12. Both the etymological and the diacritical <hi rend="italic">h</hi> have been eliminated (e.g., <hi rend="italic">havr&#xE0; &gt; 
            avr&#xE0;,</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">ninphe </hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic"> ninfe, pharetra </hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic"> faretra, herba </hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic"> erba, boscho </hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic"> bosco</hi>). In general,
          the use of <hi rend="italic">h</hi> has<hi rend="italic"> </hi>been modernized (<hi rend="italic">anc&#x2019;io</hi> &gt;  <hi rend="italic">anch&#x2019;io</hi>). In the case of <hi rend="italic">o</hi> used as interjection, it appears as <hi rend="italic">oh</hi> (unlike in
          the case of <hi rend="italic">o</hi> used as a vocative, such as in <hi rend="italic">O bellissima Licori</hi>).</p>
        <p>13. The dental affricate <hi rend="italic">ti</hi> has been changed to <hi rend="italic">zi</hi>. (e.g., <hi rend="italic">Gratie</hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic">Grazie</hi>)</p>
        <p>14. The <hi rend="italic">i</hi> devoid of any diacritical function has been eliminated.</p>
        <p>15. Compound prepositions and adverbs appear in synthetic form (e.g., <hi rend="italic">ne i</hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic">nei</hi>). However, the analytical form of the compound prepositions
      		is adopted when the synthetic form would have caused doubling of the consonant or stress change (<hi rend="italic">de le</hi>, <hi rend="italic">a la</hi>, <hi rend="italic">poi
          che</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ben che</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Al'hor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">all'hor</hi> are changed to <hi rend="italic">allor</hi>; <hi rend="italic">tal'hor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tal hor</hi> to <hi rend="italic">talor</hi>; <hi rend="italic">ogn'hor
            </hi> to <hi rend="italic">ognor</hi>.</p>
        <p>16. Typos with no apparent meaning are included in the critical apparatus because they may provide information about the typographical genesis
          and filiation of the partbooks.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Abbreviations</head>
        <div>
          <head>Voices</head>
          <p><hi rend="bold">C </hi>= Canto (<hi rend="bold">C1</hi> = Canto, first choir; <hi rend="bold">C</hi><hi rend="bold subscript">1</hi> =
            Canto, first repetition)</p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">A </hi>= Alto </p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">T </hi>= Tenore</p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">B </hi>= Basso</p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">Q </hi>= Quinto </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Other abbreviations</head>
          <p><hi rend="bold">SB </hi>= Semibrevis </p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">M </hi>= Minim </p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">SM </hi>= Semiminim</p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">F </hi>= Fusa</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
